<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<codeBook version="1.2.2" ID="zaf-roer4d-md-2017-v1" xml-lang="en" xmlns="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/DDI" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/DDI http://www.icpsr.umich.edu/DDI/Version1-2-2.xsd">
  <docDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>
          zaf-roer4d-md-2017-v1
        </titl>
      </titlStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <producer affiliation="University of Cape Town" role="Metadata producer">
          DataFirst
        </producer>
        <prodDate date="2020-04-28">
          2020-04-28
        </prodDate>
        <software version="4.0.9" date="2013-04-23">
          Nesstar Publisher
        </software>
      </prodStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version>
          Version 5
        </version>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
  </docDscr>
  <stdyDscr>
    <citation>
      <titlStmt>
        <titl>
          Research on OER for Development
        </titl>
        <subTitl>
          Metasynthesis
        </subTitl>
        <altTitl>
          ROER4DMD 2017
        </altTitl>
        <IDNo>
          zaf-roer4d-md-2017-v1
        </IDNo>
      </titlStmt>
      <rspStmt>
        <AuthEnty affiliation="University of Cape Town">
          Research on Open Educational Resources for Development
        </AuthEnty>
      </rspStmt>
      <prodStmt>
        <software version="4.0.9" date="2013-04-23">
          Nesstar Publisher
        </software>
        <fundAg abbr="IDRC" role="Funder">
          International Development Research Centre
        </fundAg>
      </prodStmt>
      <distStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Cape Town" URI="www.support.data1st.org" email="support@data1st.org">
          DataFirst support
        </contact>
      </distStmt>
      <serStmt>
        <serName>
          Education Survey [es]
        </serName>
        <serInfo>
          Research on Open Educational Resources for Development. Research on Open Educational Resources for Development Metasynthesis Dataset 2017 [dataset]. Version 1. Cape Town: ROER4D [producer], 2018. Cape Town: DataFirst [distributor], 2018. DOI: https://doi.org/10.25828/x84z-q777
        </serInfo>
      </serStmt>
      <verStmt>
        <version date="2018">
          Version 1
        </version>
      </verStmt>
    </citation>
    <stdyInfo>
      <subject>
        <keyword>
          Education
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          South Asia
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Open educational practices
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Global South
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Open educational resources
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Metasynthesis
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          South America
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Sub-Saharan Africa
        </keyword>
        <keyword>
          Southeast Asia
        </keyword>
      </subject>
      <abstract>
        <![CDATA[The Research on Open Educational Resources for Development (ROER4D) project was a four-year (2013-2017), large-scale networked project which set out to contribute to the body of research on how Open Educational Resources (OER) and address the primary research question: Whether, how, for whom and under what circumstances can engagement with open educational practices and OER provide equitable access to relevant, high-quality, affordable and sustainable education in the Global South. The project engaged a total of 103 research team members in 18 sub-projects in 21 countries across South America, Sub-Saharan Africa and South and Southeast Asia, coordinated by a central Network Hub. The research work culminated in an edited volume, Adoption and Impact of OER in the Global South. 
A primary contribution of the edited volume was the metasynthesis of sub-project findings, published as Factors influencing Open Educational Practices and OER in the Global South: Meta-synthesis of the ROER4D project. The aim of this synthesis was to distill key themes emerging from sub-project research and to identify (a) Educational challenges pertinent in the Global South context (b) Claims about OER as a mechanism to address these challenges (c) OER and related open educational practices observed in the sub-projects, as well as the structural, cultural and agential factors influencing those practices (d) Any impact that could be attributed to OER adoption in addressing educational challenges. The 13 sub-project chapters from the edited volume comprised the primary data source for the synthesis, with final research reports being utilised in two instances where there were no associated sub-project chapters.]]>
      </abstract>
      <sumDscr>
        <collDate date="2017-02" event="start"/>
        <collDate date="2017-10" event="end"/>
        <nation>
          Global South
        </nation>
        <geogCover>
          <![CDATA[Africa (Ghana, Kenya, Mauritius, South Africa, Somalia, Tanzania, Uganda, Zambia, Zimbabwe), Asia (Afghanistan,  India, Indonesia, Malaysia, Mongolia, Pakistan, Sri Lanka, The Philippines), South America (Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Uruguay)]]>
        </geogCover>
        <geogUnit>
          The data is at the level of the individual educational institution.
        </geogUnit>
        <anlyUnit>
          Other
        </anlyUnit>
        <universe>
          The study covered students and educators at secondary and tertiary institutions across the Global South.
        </universe>
        <dataKind>
          Qualitative and quantitative data
        </dataKind>
      </sumDscr>
      <notes>
        The metasynthesis used sub-project reports and chapters from the edited volume Adoption and Impact of OER in the Global South of the ROER4D sub-projects as its data, coded according to the analytical framework.
      </notes>
    </stdyInfo>
    <method>
      <dataColl>
        <dataCollector abbr="ROER4D" affiliation="University of Cape Town">
          Research on Open Educational Resources for Development
        </dataCollector>
        <collMode>
          Other [oth]
        </collMode>
        <sources/>
        <collSitu>
          This data was collected from the pre-peer reviewed chapters and reports produced by ROER4D sub-projects. Subsequent to coding, the chapters underwent a production process by edited volume publishers; therefore quoted excerpts in the edited volume may differ from the coded excerpts in this dataset.
        </collSitu>
      </dataColl>
    </method>
    <dataAccs>
      <useStmt>
        <contact affiliation="University of Cape Town" URI="support.data1st.org" email="support@data1st.org">
          DataFirst
        </contact>
        <citReq>
          Research on Open Educational Resources for Development. Research on Open Educational Resources for Development Metasynthesis Dataset 2017 [dataset]. Version 1. Cape Town: ROER4D [producer], 2018. Cape Town: DataFirst [distributor], 2018. DOI: https://doi.org/10.25828/x84z-q777
        </citReq>
        <conditions>
          Public use files, available to all
        </conditions>
      </useStmt>
    </dataAccs>
  </stdyDscr>
  <dataDscr/>
</codeBook>
