<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<codeBook version="2.5" ID="zaf-statssa-ies-2022-2023-v1" xml-lang="en" xmlns="ddi:codebook:2_5" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="ddi:codebook:2_5 https://ddialliance.org/Specification/DDI-Codebook/2.5/XMLSchema/codebook.xsd">
<docDscr>
  <citation>
    <titlStmt>
      <IDNo>zaf-statssa-ies-2022-2023-v1</IDNo>
      <titl></titl>
    </titlStmt>
    <prodStmt>
      <producer abbr="" affiliation="University of Cape Town" role="Metadata Producer">DataFirst</producer>
      <prodDate date="2025-12-17">2025-12-17</prodDate>
      <software version="v5">NADA</software>
    </prodStmt>
    <verStmt>
      <version>Version </version>
    </verStmt>
  </citation>
</docDscr>
<stdyDscr>
  <citation>
    <titlStmt>
      <titl>Income and Expenditure Survey 2022-2023</titl>
      <subTitl/>
      <altTitl>IES 2022-2023</altTitl>
      <parTitl/>
      <IDNo>zaf-statssa-ies-2022-2023-v1</IDNo>
    </titlStmt>
    <rspStmt>
      <AuthEnty affiliation="Government of South Africa">Statistics South Africa</AuthEnty>
    </rspStmt>
    <prodStmt>
      <copyright/>
      <software version="beta" date="2026-01-22">MetadataEditor</software>
      <prodDate>2025</prodDate>
      <prodPlac/>
    </prodStmt>
    <distStmt>
      <contact affiliation="University of Cape Town" URI="http://support.data1st.org/" email="support@data1st.org">DataFirst Helpdesk</contact>
      <depDate date=""/>
      <distDate date=""/>
    </distStmt>
    <serStmt>
      <serName>Income and Expenditure Survey</serName>
      <serInfo><![CDATA[]]></serInfo>
    </serStmt>
    <verStmt>
      <version date="2025">Version 1:  Edited, anonymised dataset for public distribution</version>
      <verResp/>
      <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
    </verStmt>
    <biblCit format=""><![CDATA[]]></biblCit>
    <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
  </citation>
  <studyAuthorization date="">
    <authorizingAgency affiliation="Government of South Africa" abbr="StatsSA">Statistics South Africa</authorizingAgency>
    <authorizationStatement><![CDATA[Data collection by organs of state in South Africa is authorised by the Statistics Act, 1999, and the Statistics Amendment Act, 2024]]></authorizationStatement>
  </studyAuthorization>
  <stdyInfo>
    <studyBudget><![CDATA[]]></studyBudget>
    <subject>
      <topcClas vocab="" vocabURI="">Acquisitions</topcClas>
      <topcClas vocab="" vocabURI="">Income</topcClas>
      <topcClas vocab="" vocabURI="">Expenditure</topcClas>
      <topcClas vocab="" vocabURI="">Consumption</topcClas>
    </subject>
    <abstract><![CDATA[The Income and Expenditure Survey (IES) is a household‑based survey that collects detailed data on acquisitions, consumption, spending, and income among South African households. Alongside the Living Conditions Survey (LCS), it forms part of Statistics South Africa’s household survey programme, which is essential for updating and reweighting the Consumer Price Index (CPI) to reflect evolving consumption patterns. These surveys also provide the most reliable data for assessing poverty and inequality. Previously, these two surveys were conducted on a rotating basis every 3-5 years, but due to funding limitations, Stats SA has not been able to conduct a new survey since the LCS 2014/15.

The objectives of the IES are to: establish household income and expenditure profiles; identify and reweight the Consumer Price Index (CPI) basket of goods and services based on household consumption patterns; provide inputs for developing and maintaining the household component of the National Accounts; update the country’s money‑metric, subjective, and multidimensional poverty profiles; revise inequality estimates; contribute to the rebasing of national poverty lines; and generate food security statistics.

Going forward, the survey is planned to be fully integrated into the upcoming Continuous Population Survey (CPS) programme, along with the LCS and other Continuous Data Collection (CDC) surveys such as the General Household Survey (GHS) and Domestic Tourism Survey (DTS).
]]></abstract>
    <sumDscr>
      <timePrd date="2022-11" event="start" cycle="Round 6"/>
      <timePrd date="2023-11" event="end" cycle="Round 6"/>
      <collDate date="2022-11" event="start" cycle="Round 6"/>
      <collDate date="2023-11" event="end" cycle="Round 6"/>
      <nation abbr="zaf">South Africa</nation>
      <geogCover>The survey had national coverage</geogCover>
      <geogCoverNote/>
      <geogUnit/>
      <anlyUnit><![CDATA[The units of analysis in the survey are households and individuals]]></anlyUnit>
      <universe><![CDATA[The sample for the survey included all dwelling types (domestic households, holiday homes, and all households in workers' residences, such as mining hostels and dormitories for workers). It excluded institutions such as hospitals, prisons, old-age homes, student hostels, and dormitories for scholars. Boarding houses, hotels, lodges, and guesthouses were also excluded from the sample.]]></universe>
      <dataKind>Sample survey data [ssd]</dataKind>
    </sumDscr>
    <qualityStatement>
      <standardsCompliance>
        <complianceDescription/>
      </standardsCompliance>
      <otherQualityStatement/>
    </qualityStatement>
    <notes><![CDATA[The survey measures the detailed income and expenditure of households in South Africa]]></notes>
    <exPostEvaluation completionDate="" type="">
      <evaluationProcess/>
      <outcomes/>
    </exPostEvaluation>
  </stdyInfo>
  <method>
    <dataColl>
      <timeMeth>Cross-section [cross section]</timeMeth>
      <dataCollector abbr="StatsSA" role="" affiliation="Government of South Africa">Statistics South Africa</dataCollector>
      <frequenc/>
      <sampProc><![CDATA[A total of 3, 324 Master Sample (MS) Primary Sampling Units (PSUs) were selected for the creation of an up-to-date GIF to be used in the selection of systematic sample of dwelling units (DUs) for the survey. However, during sampling process, it was realized that six (6) of the PSUs could not provide the sample due to a PSU being partly or completely demolished and PSU count being shrunk at the time of unpacking as compared to the Census 2011 count. Consequently, the resulted sample drawn consisted of 31,042 dwelling units from the 3,318 PSUs.]]></sampProc>
      <sampleFrame>
        <sampleFrameName/>
        <custodian/>
        <universe/>
        <frameUnit isPrimary="">
          <unitType numberOfUnits=""/>
        </frameUnit>
        <updateProcedure/>
      </sampleFrame>
      <deviat/>
      <collMode>Other [other]</collMode>
      <resInstru><![CDATA[The IES 2022/23 employed three instruments to gather household information: a household questionnaire, two weekly diaries, and the Classification of Individual Consumption According to Purpose (COICOP) codebook. Each instrument served a distinct function, collectively ensuring the collection of comprehensive data necessary for producing reliable income and expenditure estimates.]]></resInstru>
      <instrumentDevelopment type=""/>
      <collSitu><![CDATA[The IES 2022/23 employed a mixed-methodology combining diary and recall approaches. Respondents were asked to record their daily acquisitions of non‑durable, semi‑durable, and durable goods, as well as services, in weekly diaries over two weeks. In addition, they were required to recall acquisitions of semi‑durable and durable goods, along with selected services, for the 12 months preceding the survey month. Data collection was conducted primarily through Computer‑Assisted Personal Interviews (CAPI). Where CAPI was not feasible, Computer‑Assisted Telephonic Interviews (CATI) were implemented as a supplementary mode of data collection.
]]></collSitu>
      <actMin><![CDATA[]]></actMin>
      <ConOps><![CDATA[]]></ConOps>
      <weight><![CDATA[]]></weight>
      <cleanOps><![CDATA[]]></cleanOps>
    </dataColl>
    <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
    <anlyInfo>
      <respRate><![CDATA[]]></respRate>
      <EstSmpErr><![CDATA[]]></EstSmpErr>
      <dataAppr><![CDATA[]]></dataAppr>
    </anlyInfo>
    <stdyClas><![CDATA[]]></stdyClas>
  </method>
  <dataAccs>
    <setAvail>
      <accsPlac URI=""/>
      <origArch/>
      <avlStatus/>
      <collSize/>
      <complete/>
      <fileQnty/>
      <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
    </setAvail>
    <useStmt>
      <restrctn>Public access</restrctn>
      <contact affiliation="University of Cape Town" URI="http://www.datafirst.uct.ac.za" email="info@data1st.org">DataFirst</contact>
      <citReq><![CDATA[Statistics South Africa. Income and Expenditure 2022/2023 [dataset]. Version 1. Pretoria: Statistics South Africa [producer], 2025. Cape Town: DataFirst [distributor], 2011. DOI: 
https://doi.org/10.25828/Z52Z-RE15]]></citReq>
      <deposReq><![CDATA[Users of the data must send DataFirst a copy of or link to any publication based on the data]]></deposReq>
      <conditions><![CDATA[Creative Commons Attribution only CC-BY license]]></conditions>
      <disclaimer><![CDATA[]]></disclaimer>
    </useStmt>
    <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
  </dataAccs>
  <notes><![CDATA[]]></notes>
</stdyDscr>
<dataDscr>
</dataDscr></codeBook>
